Finding Aid for Programs for Educational Opportunity (University of Michigan) records, 1969-2002
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Programs for Educational Opportunity (University of Michigan) records 1969-2002, 1970-1986
University of Michigan. Programs for Educational Opportunity.
22 linear feet
9759 Bimu 2
A race desegregation assistance center based at the University of Michigan, the Program for Educational Opportunity was established by funding through the 1964 Civil Rights Act. The program was expanded to encompass race, gender, and national origin equity in public schools in the Great Lakes region. Administrative files, topical files, workshop and task force material, handbooks, and material pertaining to desegregation and equality in public schools in Ann Arbor, Detroit, and elsewhere in Michigan and the Great Lakes region. Includes reports from school districts and histories of desegregation.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group was received from PEO offices (Donor number 8490 ) in three accessions in June 1996, April 1997, and May 2005
The record group is open for research.
Programs for Educational Opportunity (PEO) is a race desegregation assistance center based at the University of Michigan and originally funded under Title IV of the 1964 Federal Civil Rights Act. PEO was established in 1970 under the directorship of Charles Moody and provided services to Michigan, Ohio, Illinois, Indiana, Wisconsin, and Minnesota. PEO serves as the umbrella agency for the Project for Fair Administration of School Discipline (PFASD), which was originally funded under Title VII--Emergency School Aid, Special Student Concerns Projects--and evaluates and aids midwestern school districts in eradicating incommensurate discipline of minority students. Since its inception, PEO has provided assistance to over three thousand school districts, and in-depth technical assistance to over one hundred school districts.
PEO and PFASD have served Michigan school districts in the transition period following the passing of the Civil Rights Act until the present. According to a grant proposal narrative, PEO was founded to aid both schools and students by a focus not on desegregation, but on integration to attain equality of opportunity. Furthermore, PEO and PFASD existed to address discriminatory student assignment, inequitable discipline, unrepresentative student participation, unequal counseling, discriminatory employment practices, biased curriculum, classroom segregation, interracial conflict, and community hostility toward desegregation. PEO and PFASD have supported schools seeking these goals in a number of ways. In partnership, they have conducted local, regional, and national in-service training and conferences for school districts on many topics such as human relations training, recruiting minority staff, combating racism and sexism in the curriculum, student rights and discipline, and the development of staff counseling skills. A number of reports have been issued which detail the history of desegregation in the Ann Arbor, Detroit, Ferndale, Grand Rapids, Highland Park, and Kalamazoo school districts.
PFASD also issued a number of reports both general and specific to school districts in the evaluation of schools in the equity of discipline among students. School districts were ranked at different levels within Local Education Agencies (LEAs); each district was assigned a case worker from PEO/PFASD who visited the schools on numerous occasions and reported their findings in field activities reports. Many such field activity reports were utilized to create both general and specific case studies which were then distributed to schools and/or delivered at conferences and in-service training.
PEO is now a combined Race, Gender, and National Origin Desegregation Assistance Center. The Gender Center began in 1981 and the National Origin Center in 1987. In 1988, the name was changed from the Program for Educational Opportunity to the Programs for Educational Opportunity to reflect the wider scope of its efforts. One grant currently funds all three aspects of PEO--race, gender, and national origin--and is subject to renewal every three years. While the program exists within the School of Education, there is no direct funding from the University of Michigan, nor any direct involvement by education faculty. Charles Moody remained director until 1987 when he was appointed University of Michigan Vice Provost for Minority Affairs. Upon his appointment, Percy Bates assumed directorship of the program.
The records for the Program for Educational Opportunity are divided into ten series: Administrative, Correspondence, Committees and Task Forces, Conferences and Workshops, Handbooks, Reports, Desegregation, PFASD, Public Schools, and Topical Files. All folders within series are arranged alphabetically. Researchers of desegregation efforts and the controversy of school discipline will find many valuable resources in the record group such as research reports, case studies, and conference materials. Also well documented is the Ann Arbor Area School District within the general Public Schools series which includes information on various programs within the district, records from the Board of Education, community surveys, and statistical data on staff and students. The Conferences and Workshops and Committees and Task Forces are also series that are particularly well documented; included are conference and workshop materials, reports, and in some cases, evaluations.
Subjects:
University of Michigan. Program for Educational Opportunity.; School discipline--Michigan.; Minorities--Education--Michigan.; Segregation in education--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Segregation in education--Michigan--Detroit.; Public schools--Michigan.; Educational counseling--Michigan.; Discrimination in education--Michigan.; Sex discrimination in education--Michigan.; Schools--Michigan.; University of Michigan. School of Education.; Moody, Charles D.; Multicultural education--Michigan.; School integration--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; African Americans--Education--Michigan.; University of Michigan. Center for Sex Equity in Schools.; University of Michigan. Project for the Fair Administration of Student Discipline.; University of Michigan. Programs for Educational Opportunity.
- Administrative
  The Administrative series (.75 feet) covers the years 1971-1982 and comprises budget information, PEO staff meeting minutes, and administrative papers in addition to procedure and policy information. Records detailing administrative relationships between PEO and various national and university programs and associations, such as the National Institute of Education, the Trotter House, the United Negro Fund, Inc., and the School of Social Work are located in Topical Files, the final series.
  - Budget, FY 1978 (Box 1)
  - Budget for Extension 1976-1978 (Box 1)
  - Conference Attendance 1976-1978 (Box 1)
  - Control for PEO 1978 (Box 1)
  - Expenses (Detroit) 1976-1979 (Box 1)
  - Forms
    - General 1978 (Box 1)
    - Contact Report 1977 (Box 1)
  - Local Education Agencies (LEAs)
    - High and Moderate 1977-1978 (Box 1)
    - Status Field Services 1977 (Box 1)
    - Year End Survey 1978 (Box 1)
  - Meeting Minutes
    - Component
      - 1977 (Box 1)
      - 1978 (Box 1)
    - Staff
      - 1977 (Box 1)
      - 1978 (Box 1)
  - Operating Plans undated (Box 1)
  - Policies, Staff 1976 (Box 1)
  - Procedures and Policy Manual 1976 (Box 1)
  - Reports
    - Annual, FY 1979 (Box 1)
    - Final, FY 1978, 7 folders (Box 1)
    - General Assistance Center Report for Second Quarter, FY 1978 (Box 1)
    - Interim Report of PEO, FY 1978 (Box 1)
  - Research Needs Assessment 1978 (Box 1)
  - Services
    - 1976-1978, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - FY 1978 Quarter 2 (Box 1)
    - FY 1978 Quarter 3 (Box 1)
    - (Services) Related to Sex Discrimination, FY 1978 (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  The Correspondence series (.3 feet) covers the years 1973-1982 and while not large in amount of material, contains letters and memos both from and to individuals who held positions either in the School of Education or within PEO. In most instances, titles follow the names of individuals. Correspondence is arranged chronologically by person.
  - General
    - 1977 (Box 1)
    - 1978 (Box 1)
  - Staff
    - 1977 (Box 1)
    - 1978 (Box 1)
  - Berger, Carl (Dean) 1979-1982 (Box 1)
  - Bertolaet, Fred (Assoc. Dean)
    - May 1973-March 1974 (Box 1)
    - April 1974-March 1975 (Box 1)
    - April 1975-July 1975 (Box 1)
    - September 1975-February 1979 (Box 1)
  - Burns, Eunice 1974-1977
    - 1974-1976 (Box 2)
    - 1977 (Box 2)
    - 1978-1982 (Box 2)
  - Loving, Al (Asst. Dean of Service and Institutional Relations) 1973 (Box 2)
  - Lowther, Malcolm (Asst. Dean for Instruction) 1974 (Box 2)
  - Petition Review Committee undated (Box 2)
  - Schmerl, R.B. (School of Education) 1973-1978 (Box 2)
  - Service and Institutional Relations 1978-1982 (Box 2)
  - Stark, Joan (Dean)
    - 1978 (Box 2)
    - 1979 (Box 2)
    - 1980 (Box 2)
    - 1981-1982 (Box 2)
  - Warden, Eric (Alumni Office / School of Education) 1973-1977 (Box 2)
- Committees and Task Forces
  The Committees and Task Forces series (1.25 feet) and spans the years 1969-1985. The series includes meeting minutes, relevant correspondence, and committee papers for a wide range of local and national committees having bearing upon PEO. Particularly well represented is the Affirmative Action Task Force within the School of Education. All folders are arranged alphabetically by name; task forces follow committees.
  - Committees
    - Appraisal 1973-1977 (Box 2)
    - Centennial (School of Education) 1978-1979 (Box 2)
    - Committee to Evaluate the Combined Program in Education and Psychology
      - 1969-1973 (Box 2)
      - 1974 (Box 2)
      - 1975 (Box 2)
      - January 1976-March 1976 (Box 2)
      - April 1976-September 1976 (Box 2)
      - October 1976-July 1977 (Box 2)
    - Minority Affairs Core (Box 2)
    - Multi-Cultural Committee 1964-1979, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - Multi-Ethnic Committee 1975-1983 (Box 2)
    - Multi-Ethnic School Environments (MESE)
      - 1977 (Box 2)
      - 1978 (Box 2)
      - January 1979-April 1979 (Box 2)
      - May 1979-October 1979 (Box 2)
    - Pound House Children's Center 1975-1976 (Box 2)
    - Professional Development Committee
      - 1981 (Box 2)
      - January 1982-August 1982 (Box 2)
      - September 1982 (Box 2)
      - November 1982-December 1982 (Box 2)
      - January 1983 (Box 2)
      - February 1983-June 1983 (Box 2)
      - August 1983-December 1983 (Box 2)
      - 1984 (Box 2)
      - Report on Graduate Credit for Professional Development 1983 (Box 2)
    - Rackham Faculty Selection 1981-1983 (Box 2)
    - Research
      - Finley Carpenter Research Conference 1982 (Box 2)
      - Meeting Minutes 1972-1977, 1982-1985, 2 folders (Box 2)
      - Research Coordinating Committee Meeting Minutes 1972-1973 (Box 2)
    - Roberto Clemente Student Development Center Advisory Committee 1974-1975 (Box 2)
    - School Desegregation (National) 1982 (Box 3)
    - School of Education
      - Grant Awards Activity 1971-1981 (Box 3)
      - Review
        - 1982 (Box 3)
        - Grant Statistics 1970-1982 (Box 3)
      - Transition Team 1983 (Box 3)
    - Senate Advisory on University Affairs 1974-1975 (Box 3)
    - Service and Institutional Relations 1973-1979 (Box 3)
    - Student Petition Review 1973-1979 (Box 3)
    - Students for Educational Innovation 1976 (Box 3)
    - University Relations Advisory Committee 1975-1977 (Box 3)
    - Uses of Detroit Rackham Building (Ad Hoc) 1981 (Box 3)
    - Women's Program Coordinator Search Committee 1974 (Box 3)
  - Task Forces
    - Affirmative Action (School of Education)
      - 1971-1975 (Box 3)
      - 1976-1981 (Box 3)
      - January 1982-July 1982 (Box 3)
      - August 1982-December 1982 (Box 3)
    - Drug / Crime 1975 (Box 3)
    - Innovative Teacher Education 1973-1976 (Box 3)
    - Leadership in Ann Arbor 1984 (Box 3)
    - Technology 1982-1983 (Box 3)
- Conferences and Workshops
  The Conferences and Workshops series (1.75 feet) covers 1971-1983 and is one of the largest series within the collection. It includes not only planning materials for conferences, but also the reports both generated and, in some cases, presented at conferences and workshops. Papers presented by PEO director Charles Moody appear at the end of the series prior to Workshops. A virtually comprehensive index to conferences between 1971-1977 is located at the beginning of the series, in addition to conference evaluation results from 1973-1974. Information on workshops includes in-service training and special school presentation materials. Planning materials and handouts are included. Conferences and workshops were geared mainly towards educators and focused on many issues such as bicultural education, humanistic education, developing counseling skills, diversity in educational opportunities, and student suspensions and discipline. Conferences and workshops are arranged alphabetically by title. Workshop information follows conference materials.
  - Conferences
    - Index to Conference Titles 1971-1977 (Box 3)
    - Evaluation Results 1973-1974 (Box 3)
    - "Administrative and Legal Implications of Desegregation," 5/1971 (Box 3)
    - "Alternative Education in a Pluralistic Society," 6/1973 (Box 3)
    - "Beyond Desegregation--The Educational and Legal Issues," 4/1974 (Box 3)
    - "Bilingual-Bicultural Education," 12/1975, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - "Bilingual-Bicultural Education: Where Are We? Where Are We Going?" 3/1977 (Box 3)
    - "Collective Negotiation and Desegregation: Issues in the Public Schools," c1971-c1972
      - Conference Materials November, 1971 (Box 3)
      - "Ann Arbor Education Association vs. Board of Education, 1971-1972" (Box 3)
    - "Combating Racism and Sexism in Curriculum and Library Materials," 3/1976 (Box 3)
    - "Cultural Pluralism: Curriculum Assessment, Development, and Implementation," 11/1976 (Box 3)
    - "Curricular, Instructional, and Supervisory Decision Making to Meet Changing Educational Needs," 5/1973 (Box 3)
    - "Desegregation Problems, Approaches, and Resources," 10/1978 (Box 3)
    - "Developments in School Desegregation and the Law," 5/1972, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - "Diversity in Educational Opportunities," 3/1974 (Box 3)
    - "Educational Policies and Equal Educational Opportunity," 5/1973 (Box 3)
    - "Equal Educational Opportunity in High School Athletics," 3/1975, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - "Humanistic Education in the Desegregated Classroom," 12/1976 (Box 3)
    - "Intercultural Communication in the School Setting," 4/1978 (Box 3)
    - "Minority Teacher Recruitment," 5/1978 (Box 3)
    - "Model for Human Relations: Tools for Communicating," 11/1979 (Box 3)
    - "Multi-Cultural Curriculum and Instruction," 11/1978, 3 folders (Box 4)
    - "Multi-Ethnic Curriculum and the Changing Role of the Teacher," 6/1972 (Box 4)
    - "Overcoming Segregation and Discrimination: Recent Legal and Educational Developments," 5/1976 (Box 4)
    - PEO
      - Orientation in re: Desegregation 10/1978, 3 folders (Box 4)
      - Summer Conference Proceedings 1971 (Box 4)
    - "Personnel in the Desegregation Process," 5/1972 (Box 4)
    - "School Desegregation: Plans and Processes a Quarter Century after Brown," 4/1979 (Box 4)
    - "School Desegregation, Public Information and the Media," 5/1973 (Box 4)
    - "Sexism / Title IX," 1/1976 (Box 4)
    - "Spring Michigan Quarterly Conference on Desegregation," 6/1977 (Box 4)
    - "Student Behavior, Rights and Responsibilities and the Fair Administration of Discipline," 4/1974 (Box 4)
    - "Student Participation and Treatment," 2/1979 (Box 4)
    - "Student Suspensions and Discipline, " 5/1978 (Box 4)
    - "Supreme Court and Due Process in School Discipline," 4/1975 (Box 4)
    - "Teacher Training Institutions and the Need for Multi-Cultural Education," 4/1974 (Box 4)
    - "Title IX: An Avenue to Effective Learning in Physical Education at the Secondary School Level," 6/1978 (Box 4)
    - "Title IX: Physical Education in the Secondary Schools," 3/1978 (Box 4)
    - "Women and Men Working with Boys and Girls in Physical Education and Athletics," 12/1976 (Box 4)
  - Papers Presented by Charles Moody, head of PEO
    - "Administrative Leadership--Educators' Attitudes and Pupil Achievement," 11/1979 (Box 4)
    - "Blacks and Other Third World People in Administration," undated (Box 4)
    - "Education for the Twenty-First Century: A Black Agenda," 11/1978 (Box 4)
    - Founder's Banquet: Omega Psi Phi Fraternity 4/1979 (Box 4)
    - "Implications of Desegregation for Black Students, Teachers, and Administrators," 4/1974 (Box 4)
    - "Improving the Effectiveness of Urban Education: A Desegregation / Integration Issue," 4/1978 (Box 4)
    - "Stress Factors in Desegregation: Some Issues to be faced by Elementary Principals," 10/1977 (Box 4)
  - Workshops
    - Code of Conduct Committee Training Session 3/1982 (Box 4)
    - "Current Information and Approaches in Student Rights and School Discipline: A Monthly Symposium" (Box 4)
    - "Human Relations," 1970-1971 (Box 4)
    - "Humanistic Education," 12/1976 (Box 4)
    - "In-Service Education for School Personnel in Curricular, Instructional, and Supervisory Decision Making," 1973 (Box 4)
    - "Moderate Intensity Districts, Regions I-III," 1978 (Box 4)
    - "Staff Development of Consultant Skills," 5/1983, 3 folders (Box 4)
    - "Staff Utilization of Para-Professionals," 12/1974 (Box 4)
    - "Student Advisory Committees," 2/1974 (Box 4)
    - "Student Discipline," 1978 (Box 4)
    - "Student Rights and Discipline: Procedures, Policies, and Programs," 3/1977 (Box 4)
    - "Student Rights and Responsibilities--Detroit Public Schools," 1970, 3 folders (Box 5)
    - "University Values," 1974-1976 (Box 5)
- Handbooks
  The Handbooks series (.5 feet) spans 1973-1979 and contains handbooks and manuals created by PEO for referral and training purposes, but is not comprehensive. Included are manuals on conference planning, implementing a multi-cultural curriculum, and inter-cultural approaches to a multi-cultural education. Administration, Desegregation and PFASD manuals can be located within those series.
  - Conference Planning, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - "Implementing a Multi-Cultural Curriculum," 1979 (Box 5)
  - "Intercultural Approaches to a Multi-Cultural Education," c1973 (Box 5)
  - "Student Advisory Committee Training Model, Phase II," 1975-1976, 3 folders (Box 5)
- Reports
  The Reports series (.5 feet) covers ca. 1975-ca. 1982, and is small in size as it constitutes only general reports. Researchers should note the existence of specialized reports in other series, such as Desegregation and PFASD. Reports in this series are general in nature with the exception of the proposal for a race desegregation center. Other report titles include "Approaches to Equity" and "Cultural Encounters: Some Truths about the Melting Pot."
  - "Approaches to Equity," undated (Box 5)
  - "Cultural Encounters: Some Truths about the Melting Pot," 1975 (Box 5)
  - "Equity Based Education and Planned Change," undated (Box 5)
  - "Readings in Equalizing Educational Opportunity and School Desegregation," undated (Box 5)
  - "Social Studies Unit on Cultural Diversity," 1978, 6 folders (Box 5)
  - "Students' Rights and Responsibilities, Historical Overview," 1979 (Box 5)
- Desegregation
  The Desegregation series (1 foot) covers 1972-1981, and is divided into public schools, and contains reports specific to those schools. Histories of desegregation efforts from 1954 to 1979 within many schools are included in addition to a small amount of school-specific desegregation proposal and resource materials. Detroit is particularly well represented by a lengthy "Battle to Desegregate Detroit's Schools, 1954-1979." Following the public schools are three general folders on desegregation: "Planning Handbook," "Status of Desegregation in Michigan," and a topical information packet.
  - Ann Arbor
    - Desegregation, A Case Study of, c1977 (Box 5)
    - Desegregation in Ann Arbor Public Schools, A History of 1954-1976 (Box 5)
  - Detroit
    - "The Battle to Desegregate Detroit's Schools, 1954-1977"
      - Report, 2 folders (Box 5)
      - Appendix I, Court Orders, 3 folders (Box 5)
      - Appendix II, Reports and Plans, 3 folders (Box 6)
      - Appendix III, Board Minutes, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Ferndale
    - Desegregation of the Ferndale Schools, A History 1954-1977 (Box 6)
    - "Forum Series," undated (Box 6)
  - Grand Rapids
    - Desegregation, A History of 1954-1979 (Box 6)
    - Desegregation, A Proposal for 1972, 3 folders (Box 6)
  - Highland Park
    - Integration Proposal Materials 1973, 6 folders (Box 6)
    - "Identifying and Utilizing Resources for School Desegregation," 1979 (Box 6)
  - Kalamazoo
    - Desegregation, A History (Update) 1976-1981 (Box 6)
    - Desegregation, History of 1981 (Box 6)
  - Willow Run
    - Desegregation, A Case Study of School 1954-1976 (Box 6)
    - "Planning Handbook", 2 folders (Box 6)
    - "Status of Desegregation in Michigan," 1978 (Box 6)
    - Topical Information Packet, 3 folders (Box 6)
- Project for the Fair Administration of School Discipline (PFASD)
  The Project for the Fair Administration of School Discipline (PFASD) series (3.5 feet) covers the years 1974-1980. It contains administrative meeting minutes, reference and training manuals, and papers concerning public schools. School-specific reports and many schools' codes of behavior and rights statements are included in this series. Ann Arbor is not particularly well represented in this series; Lansing, Buena Vista, and Detroit are the best represented schools. Following the breakdown of materials by school are general papers of PFASD. Included is the original proposal for the establishment of PFASD, and research reports and implementation plans of PFASD. Concluding the series is information on PFASD-specific workshops. The largest amount of materials concerning workshops concerns "Building Class Rules."
  - Administrative
    - Meeting Minutes 1978-1979 (Box 6)
  - Manuals
    - "Basic Interpersonal Classroom Communication," 5/1978 (Box 6)
    - "Cumulative Reference Manual," 1976, 4 folders (Box 6)
    - "Evaluating Discipline in the Schools," undated (Box 7)
    - "Friction Program," 1980, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - "Model for Discipline System Procedures Manual," undated (Box 7)
  - Public Schools
    - "Building and District Codes /Report Formats," 1976 (Box 7)
    - "Cross District Analysis of 1974-1975 School Discipline Data, 3 folders (Box 7)
    - "District Policy", 3 folders (Box 7)
    - "Law and Policies on Student Tardiness," circa 1980 (Box 7)
    - "Report to Participating Staff on the 1975-1976 PFASD of Parents, Teachers, and Students of School Four" (Box 7)
    - "Response to the Open Letter to Richard Staff," 10/1978, 2 folders
      - "School Four" (Box 7)
    - Staff Report Forms 1977, 3 folders (Box 7)
    - Survey Form and Feedback by District, 5 folders (Box 7)
    - Teacher Critique of School Policies, c1978 (Box 7)
    - Teacher Questionnaires circa 1980 (Box 7)
    - Ann Arbor
      - Codes of Behavior and Rights Statements 1970-1972, 1979 (Box 7)
    - Birmingham
      - Codes of Behavior and Rights Statements 1971 (Box 7)
    - Buena Vista
      - General, 1973- circa 1980 (Box 7)
      - Discipline Measures circa 1978 (Box 7)
      - Discipline Team 1976-1977 (Box 7)
      - Student Court 1976 (Box 7)
      - Student Rights and Discipline Handbook 1976-1978 (Box 7)
      - Title VII Program 1975-1976, 3 folders (Box 7)
    - Detroit
      - Board of Education Policy Statement 1971 (Box 7)
      - Code of Conduct 1976 (Box 7)